Whyte, William Foote Additional Papers /4094
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
William Foote Whyte Additional Papers
1974-1988
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Whyte, William Foote.
/4094
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
7984561
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
C. Tan, June 17, 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, September 30, 2016
Biographical / Historical
William Foote Whyte (June 27, 1914-July 16, 2000) was a sociologist chiefly known for his ethnographic study in urban sociology, Street Corner Society. Whyte, from an upper middle class background, showed an early interest in writing, economics and social reform. After graduating from Swarthmore College, he was selected for the Junior Fellows program, where his landmark research was done. After his research in Boston, he entered the sociology doctoral program at the University of Chicago. Street Corner Society was published by the University of Chicago Press in 1943. He spent a year teaching at the University of Oklahoma, but developed polio in 1943 and spent two years in physical therapy at the Warm Springs Foundation. Rehabilitation was only partially successful; Whyte walked with a cane for the rest of his life, and used two arm crutches in his later years. He briefly returned to the University of Chicago in 1944, then joined the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in 1948, remaining at Cornell for the remainder of his career. He worked for social reform and social change, directing his efforts toward "empowering the disenfranchized and narrowing the gap between rich and poor." He studied industrial and agricultural workers and workers' cooperatives in Venezuela, Peru, Guatemala and in the Basque region of Spain, as well as in the United States. He authored hundreds of articles and 20 books including an autobiography. He is considered a pioneer in industrial sociology.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4149 AV: "ASA Award Presentation to William Foote Whyte by Jacqueline Scheier" Audio-Visual Materials /4058: William Foote Whyte Office Records /4087: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4102: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4149: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4151: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4163: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4168: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4173: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers
Whyte, William Foote, 1914-2000
7984561
- Greenwood Gonzalez Project Participatory Action Research in FAGOR (1 of 2), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Greenwood Gonzales Project Participatory Action Research in FAGOR (2 of 2), 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- ULGOR Documents for Constitution and By-laws, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Spain & Basque Governments Legal Documents, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- La Experiencia de Mondragon como Proceso, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Reports & Planning Documents (1 of 2), 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Reports & Planning Documents (2 of 2), 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- ULARCO Documents, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- ULARCO Documents, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- ULARCO Documents, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Group of Cooperatives at Mondragon, 1976-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- JMA & Coop Theory Documents, Translations, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Mondragon Documents, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- WFW Interviews, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Employee Notices- Strike Settlement Agreement, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Clippings from Trabajo Union, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Adapting the Mondragon Experience, readings, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Reports of Others, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Mondragon Experiment, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Azurmendi, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- ANA and WFW Interviews, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- The FAGOR Group of Mondragon, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Ana Johnson Thesis, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Mondragon Books, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Scope and Contents
  Spanish
- Actualidad Sociolaboral, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Worker Owners The Mondragon Achievement, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Trabajo y Union, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Trabajo y Union, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Memoria Ejercicio, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Caja Laboral Popular Lan Kide Avrrezkia, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Ikerlan Memoria, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Eroski Memoria, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Fagor Annual Reports, Catalogue, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Caja Laboral Popular Lan Kide Avrrezkia, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Annual Reports Caja Laboral Popular, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Experiencia Cooperativa, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Caja Laboral Popular Cooperative Group, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Caja Laboral Analysis, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Ularco Memoria, 1978-1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Mondragon Cooperatives Dissertation, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- The Creation of Industrial Cooperatives in the Basque Country Dissertation, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)